Hi Anabelle, Can you please introduce
yourself for this project. This is the second subtitle
Yes. My name is
Anabelle Contreras-Castro,
and I am a professor in the National
University of Costa Rica.
I am a professor in the school
of Scenic Arts,
and I direct a doctoral program,
which is called
the Discipline of Arts and
Letters in Central America.
Thank you.
How is Performance Studies
understood in Costa Rica?
Well, until recently, it was a
relatively unknown field;
we never had a performance studies
movement like other countries had.
We had artists who did performance,
some without knowing it,
some did know,
and some people who had written some,
but there were no formal studies
in the academy.
So, from there, we had the idea to
introduce performance studies
in the National University in the
school of Scenic Arts,
and we created
a formal degree program
in which we introduced performance
studies
as a mode of research,
and also practice,
with some concepts
we had been needing,
and also to break up a little
the direction the school had been
going, which was exclusively theater.
So there was, let’s say, a debate,
or a conflict,
between theater and visual arts,
in relation to performance,
if it was interesting as practice
or as methodology?
I don’t think it was an open debate,
not a prior conflict.
What there was first was the seminar,
and the doubts came later,
because
the seminar had really positive
results,
and immediately people began to doubt
if the theater school should take
that path or not.
It didn’t generate an open debate,
and so we have until today an
optional course
that began as being part of the
School for Scenic Arts
and today is open to all the
university,
so we receive students from
all disciplines,
who do their optional course
in Performance Studies,
half as a theoretical course,
the other half as practice.
And where do you get your
theoretical texts?
That is a problem in the smaller
countries
like in Central America,
where
they don’t import large quantities
of books,
books are
very expensive because they have
very high import taxes,
and so we have a fairly informal
and illegal system.
This is to say, we photocopy books,
we clone them,
we scan them, and we find ways
to circulate knowledge
that are informal and illegal.
Ok, good.
Which are the theorists with the
strongest presence here?
Well, we have worked a great deal
with Diana Taylor’s books,
and some other virtual periodicals.
The virtual periodical from the
Hemispheric Institute
has been really important for us,
as well as
some theorists from Brazil,
South America,
some connected to the Hemispheric
Institute,
and other things we find
on the internet,
because in the bookstores you
can’t find
almost any of this stuff.
Yes. Is there anyone here who
works on these themes?
Performance Studies?
Yes, who publishes on this,
in theoretical terms?
We have many more practice-based works
than theoretical at this moment.
This is to say, the elective course
given
by the university
is a place to explore
concepts of the body.
It’s very difficult here that they
understand
in the cultural sector
that you have to intellectually
produce artists
as doers, but more as thinkers
about what they are doing,
and we’re trying to generate material,
but there isn’t much.
Ok, thank you very much.
My pleasure.